嗨! 大家好，我Jiun
Hi everyone, my name is Jiun.
感謝你找到我的頻道並觀看我的視頻
Welcome to my channel and thank you for watching my video.
今天我們不打皂我們來聊一聊火山爆發!
Today we are going to talk about Volcano Eruption!
耶耶耶！大家先不要急著退出影片！
Don't skip this video yet!
你們沒有來錯地方
You are at the right place,
這裡依然是講述有關手工皂的 YouTube Channel
we are still a YouTube Channel for handmade soap.
可是今天要講的火山爆發
But the "volcano eruption" that we will be talking about today
不是這種
is not this type of volcano eruption
而是這一種
but Soap Volcano.
我在之前製作家事皂的影片裡就答應過大家
In my previous video of making household soap,
會專門製作一期影片來和大家說一說
I promised everyone that I will be making a special episode to talk about
為什麼手工皂會裂開
why does handmade soap crack,
尤其是家事皂真的特別容易會裂開
especially household soap.
而我們又要如何避免這個問題呢？
But how do we overcome this problem?
那在開始講述之前那我先帶大家去看一看照片
Before we begin, let's take a look at some photos
讓大家有個概念到底肥皂火山爆發
So that everyone has an idea of
長什麼樣子
how Soap Volcano looks like
首先我們來到谷歌大神的家
First, we come to Google
搜索關鍵詞Soap Volcano
type the keywords "Soap Volcano" on the search bar.
你也可以用中文搜索
You can also search the keywords in Mandarin,
肥皂裂開
肥皂火山爆發
之類的關鍵詞也能找到相關圖片
These keywords can also help you to find relevant pictures.
可是如果使用英文搜索的話能找到更多相關圖片
But you can find more relevant pictures using English keywords.
我們先來看看這張圖片
First let us take a look at this photo.
肥皂表面完全裂開
The surface of the soap is totally cracked.
裡面的肥皂快要噴發出來
The soap is about to volcano out of the mold.
現在大家明白
Now you understand
為什麼我們稱這個現象為肥皂火山爆發了吧？
why this phenomenon is known as Soap Volcano right?
我們再看看第2張圖片
Now look at the second picture.
這個呢就更嚴重了
This is more serious,
皂液就像火山岩漿一樣全部噴灑出來
the soap is blasting out of the mold like lava.
接下來我們看看第3張圖片
Next we look at the third picture.
這個現像我們稱之為Alien Brain
We call this phenomenon as Alien Brain.
因為他的皺褶看起來就有點像外星人的腦袋
Because the wrinkles on the top make the surface looks like alien's brain.
那他形成的原因呢
I will explain
我待會也會一起告訴大家
the cause of this phenomenon later.
那接下來這張圖片呢
The next picture here is what happened in my last video,
是我之前製作家事皂影片時出現的裂開狀況
the household soap was cracked on top.
拍攝這張照片時
When I took this picture,
肥皂還在皂化中
the soap was still in saponification.
中間那一圈就是果凍
This is the Gel Phase.
而這張圖片呢
But this picture here
就是肥皂完全皂化後的樣子
shows how the soap looks like after saponification.
果凍消失了
The gel phase disappears,
只剩下中間的裂痕
left with a huge crack at the center.
那待會我會告訴大家我做了哪個舉動
Later I will tell you some of the steps
讓我在製作第2次時
I have taken during the 2nd time of making the soap
使用了同樣的配方和模具
using the same ingredients and mold
可是卻沒有裂開
and it did not crack.
完美大成功！
An absolute success!
那剛才我們看到了三個不同程度的裂開現象
So just now we have seen three different degrees of cracked soap tops.
雖然第3張圖他沒有裂開
Although the soap in the third picture did not crack,
可是它產生皺紋的原因是一樣的
but the cause for its wrinkles is the same as cracked soap top,
所以我就在這里和大家一起講述
so I will explain them altogether.
那造成肥皂裂開和產生Alien Brain的原因都是同一個
So cracked soap tops and Alien Brain are caused by the same problem
那就是
which is
高溫
overheating.
如果你有製作手工皂的經驗你應該有發覺到
If you have experience in making handmade soap,
當皂液入模以後的30分鐘至一小時以後
you might realize that after filling the mold with soap for 30 minutes to 1 hour
當你再去觸碰模具時你能感覺到他是溫熱的
the mold container will feels hot.
那是因為肥皂在皂化過程中會升溫發熱
This is because the soap continues to heat up during saponification.
而如果溫度實在是飆升得太高
and if the temperature gets too high,
就會造成火山爆發
it will cause Soap Volcano.
那由於肥皂的周圍都有模具包圍著
The soap is enclosed within the mold
只有表面能散熱
where heat can only escape via the top surface.
所以肥皂裂開的地方
So the soap usually cracks
都在肥皂表面
on the top surface.
那到底有哪些原因導致肥皂溫度過高
So what are the other reasons that cause overheating
進而引起火山爆發呢？
leading to Soap Volcano?
主要原因有四個
There are 4 main reasons,
第一：油鹼混合時溫度太高
Firstly, the temperature of lye solution and oils was too high during mixing.
第二：你使用的模具有很好的保溫效果
Secondly, the mold you are using has very good heat insulating properties.
第三
Thirdly,
當皂液入模以後你把他放在一個保溫效果很好的地方
you put the soap in places with thermal insulation after it is molded.
例如：保溫箱或是烤箱
For instance, cooler box or oven.
第四：你使用了某些帶有升溫效果的添加物
Lastly, you used additives that produce heat naturally.
例如：含有蛋白質的添加物
For example, additives that contain protein,
牛奶、羊奶、母乳和豆漿這些都算
including cow milk, goat milk, breastmilk and soy milk.
含有糖分的添加物
And high natural sugar ingredients,
例如：蜂蜜
such as honey.
含有酒精成分的添加物
Additives that contain alcohol
例如大家很喜歡製作的啤酒皂和紅酒皂
that can be found in the popular beer and wine soaps
還有就是某些精油和香精
and some fragrance oils or essential oils
也會導致溫度上升
can also cause the temperature of soap to rise.
那根據我之前使用的經驗與大家分享
Based on my previous experience,
大部分花類的香精或精油都會造成皂液升溫的效果
most floral fragrance oils or essential oils  will cause the rise in temperature of soap.
當然這不僅此於花類的精油或香精
But of course it is not only limited to floral essential oils or fragrance oils,
其他類別的精油或香精也是有可能會導致溫度上升的
other essential oils or fragrance oils might also cause the temperature to rise.
那由於精油和香精的品牌和類別實在是太多
But there are countless of essential oils and fragrance oils in the market
而且他們成分複雜
and they have complicated ingredients,
我在這裡無法為大家一一舉出
so I cannot list them out one-by-one in this video.
而且我本身也並不是專業的香氛師
Plus I am not a professional perfumer or fragrance expert.
我只是根據我之前使用的經驗與大家分享
I can only share my knowledge based on my past experience,
那如果有什麼遺漏的地方歡迎大家留言補充
so feel free to comment down below if you have anything to add on.
那接下來我們來講一下
So now let's us talk about
到底要如何避免肥皂裂開或是火山爆發
how to prevent cracked soap tops or Soap Volcano.
一共有6點要和大家分享
There are 6 points to share with you:
第一：油鹼混合時把溫度控制在30°c左右
Number 1: Keep the temperature of the mixture of lye solutions and oils around 30 degree celsius.
溫度相差兩三度沒關係
Slight difference in temperature should be fine,
可是如果你是製作家事皂的話
but if you are making household soap,
最好把溫度控制在30°c以下
it is best to keep the temperature below 30 degree celsius.
第二：選用保溫效果比較低的模具
Number 2: choose a less insulating mold.
例如：比較薄的矽膠模
For instance, silicone molds with thinner walls
或是沒有木盒的吐司模
or non-wood loaf mold.
第三：如果是在夏天的話皂液入模以後可以選擇不要保溫
Number 3: you can choose not to insulate your newly-molded soap during the summer
然後把肥皂放在一個通風涼爽的地方
and put it at a dry and cool place if needed.
第四點：
Number 4:
避免使用帶有升溫效果的添加物
Avoid using naturally heat-producing additives,
就是我們之前提到的那些
the ones we mentioned previously,
帶有蛋白質成分
those ingredients that contain protein,
糖分
sugar,
還有酒精成分的材料
and alcohol,
還有某些香精和精油
as well as some essential oils or fragrance oils.
第五點：把水量的倍數拉高
Number 5: increase the ratio of water
或是把軟油的比例拉高
or increase the ratio of soft oils.
當水量增加皂化的速度就會變慢
When the amount of water increases, the saponification process will get slower
那升溫的速度也會跟著放慢
and the heating process will also become slower,
也就沒那麼容易裂開了
thus reducing the likelihood of cracking.
可是如果水量太多的話肥皂就會偏軟噢
However, the soap will get overly soft if you add too much water.
大家也要把這一點考慮進去
Please take this into consideration as well.
而如果增加軟油比例
But if you increase the ratio of soft oils,
那肥皂就沒有那麼硬
the soap will not be too hardened,
也就沒那麼容易裂開了
and it will not crack easily.
第六
Number 6:
如果你是製作高比例椰子油手工皂
If you are making handmade soap with high proportion of coconut oil,
例如：椰子油家事皂
for instance, coconut oil household soap.
那你就可以考慮
Then you can consider
打開電風扇對著他
cooling the soap using electronic fan.
又或是放進冰箱的冷藏區幫助降溫
Or you can put the soap into the fridge to help it cool down.
也就是放蔬菜水果的那一區
It's the compartment of the fridge where you put your fruits and vegetables,
那大家要注意哦！
please take note!
我這裡說的是高比例的椰子油手工皂配方
The example I am giving here is the handmade soap with high proportion of coconut oil
並不是所有的手工皂配方都放入冰箱裡做降溫
which means not all handmade soaps are suitable to be placed into fridge for cooling.
例如手工皂的配方裡
For instance,
椰子油的比例佔有80%至100%
if the proportion of coconut oil is around 80% to 100% in a soap,
就屬於高比例
then the proportion is considered high.
因為在眾多手工皂配方裡
Among all the handmade soap recipes,
高比椰子油的配方
the coconut oil recipe
是最容易引起火山爆發或是裂開的
is most likely to cause cracked tops or Soap Volcano.
因為椰子油的硬度很高、皂化速度快、升溫速度也快
Coconut oil is considered a hard oil which induces fast saponification and speeds up the heating process.
如果你是製作100%椰子油家事皂
If you are making a 100% coconut oil household soap,
那配方裡就完全沒有軟油
the recipe does not contain soft oil at all.
如果再配上一個保溫效果很好的模具
And if you use a mold with good thermal insulating properties...
大家聽到我說把肥皂放入冰箱裡降溫
You might think that it's weird
可能會覺得很奇怪
to put soap into the fridge for cooling,
尤其是亞洲的打皂人
especially for Asian soapmakers.
可是在西方國家這是很普遍的做法
But this is actually a very common method in Western countries.
我本身也測試過這個方法
I myself have tried this method
而我的家事皂也健康的順產了
and my household soap was successfully made.
那在西方國家和我們東方國家的打皂方法上
There are indeed some differences in soap making methods
的確是有某些地方的差異
between Western and Eastern countries.
例如在西方國家他們會把烤箱預熱以後
For instance, Western soapmakers usually preheat the oven,
關火
turn off the oven
然後把肥皂放入烤箱裡做保溫
and then only place the soap into oven to keep it warm.
可是在我們這裡呢一般是使用保溫箱做保溫
However, we Asians usually use cooler box to keep the soap warm。
保溫的話
To keep the soap warm,
就放入烤箱
we put it into the oven.
降溫的話
For cooling purposes,
就放入冰箱
we put it into the fridge.
沒毛病啊！
There's no problem at all!
那大家如果覺得好奇以上方法的話可以親自測試看看
You can try it yourself if you are interested,
可是記得安全第一
but remember safety comes first.
要搜索好資料做好功課才去測試
Do sufficient research before trying out this method.
那我再和大家仔細的說一下
Now I will have to further explain
剛才我提到的方法
the method that I have mentioned earlier
大家需要靈活變通的去使用
requires certain flexibility and adaptibility.
畢竟每個人生活的環境都不一樣
Since everyone has different living conditions,
必須要根據當下的氣溫、氣候還有個人使用的模具
you have to make adjustments
去做調整
according to your surrounding temperature, climate and the soap making tools you use.
為了讓大家有更好的理解
To give you a better idea,
我在這裡為大家舉幾個例子
I will provide a few examples.
如果說現在是在夏天
For instance, imagine it's summer now
而你的油鹼溫度是在40°c左右
and your soap mixture is around 40 degrees celsius,
在這麼炎熱的夏天這麼高的油鹼溫度
then your soap is very likely to crack
肥皂是很容易會裂開的
under such high temperatures.
那在這時你可以選用一些比較薄的模具
Now you can choose to use molds with thinner walls
皂液入模以後選擇不要保溫
and choose not to insulate the newly-molded soap.
因為據我所知
Because according to what I know,
有些皂友
some of the soapmaker
是喜歡使用40°c左右的溫度去打皂的
like to make soap under the temperature of around 40 degrees celsius.
那這時
By this time,
你並不需要強逼自己改掉這個習慣
you don't have to force yourself to change this habit
去把溫度降至30°c
by reducing the temperature to 30 degrees celsius.
而是可以在模具、水量
You can choose to make adjustments on
或是皂液入模以後放置肥皂的地方去做調整
the type of mold, the water portion and the storage place after molding.
那如果說現在是在寒冷的冬天
But imagine it's winter now,
而你唯一的模具是這種薄薄的模具
and the only mold you have is thin-walled mold,
那又該怎麼辦呢？
what should you do then?
那你可以從一開始就把油鹼溫度控制在高一些
You can keep the temperature of soap mixture higher in the beginning of soapmaking process
添加一些牛奶幫助升溫
or add some milk to help raise the temperature
皂液入模以後放入保溫箱做保溫
and put the mold into cooler box to keep it warm.
可是如果你使用的模具是這種比較厚的模具
However, if you use this type of mold with thicker walls
而且還是帶蓋子的
and with wonden box and lid
那你可以選擇不要保溫也是可以的
then you can choose not to insulate the soap.
我用家事皂再舉一個例子
I will give one more example of household soap
因為家事皂實在是很容易裂開
because household soap really cracks easily
尤其是對於新手來說每次遇到都手足無措
which is especially challenging for newbies.
如果你製作家事皂使用的模具
If the mold you use for making household soap
是這種比較單薄的模具
is a thin-walled mold like this
又或是這種PP5的塑料盒
or a PP5 plastic container like this
他們的散熱效果都很好
they have very good heat dissipating properties,
所以一般情況下是不會裂開的
so the soap will not crack easily under such conditions
所以也就不需要放入冰箱裡降溫了
and there is no need to put the soap into fridge for cooling.
可是如果你製作家事皂是使用這種保溫性很好的模具
But if you use mold with good insulating properties like this,
那裂開的可能性是蠻高的
there is a high possibility of soap cracking.
那這時呢你可以考慮
Now you can consider
當皂液入模以後
to cool down the soap
把他放入冰箱的冷藏區做降溫
by putting it into the fridge
又或是開著電風扇吹著他
or placing it in front of a fan.
當然你也需要把你當下的環境溫度考慮進去
Of course you have to take your surrounding temperature into account
需不需要做這個舉動
to see if it's necessary to exercise this step.
製作手工皂的程序看似簡單
The steps for making handmade soap might seem easy,
可是當中的細節和原理才是需要我們深入的去學習
but there are a lot of details and principles that we need to take into account.
那進步最好的方法
The best way to improve
就是多練習
is to practice regularly
又或者是多來看看我的影片
or watch more of my videos.
那你們喜歡這一類純分享手工皂知識的影片嗎？
Do you like videos of me sharing about soapmaking knowledge?
如果大家喜歡的話以後我會多分享這一類影片
I will share more videos like this if you are interested.
歡迎你留言告訴我
Feel free to drop a comment down below.
如果你喜歡我今天的影片
If you like this video,
請給我點個贊
don't forget to hit the like button below,
記得要訂閱我的頻道和打開小鈴鐺
subscribe my channel and turn on the notification.
感謝你的觀看！我們下個影片見！
Thank you for watching! See you in my next video!